A Finding Aid to the Thomas Carr Howe papers, 1932-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.howethom
Archives of American Art
- Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Records and Looted Art Inventories, circa 1942-1950; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3, 5, OV 6
  - Looted Art Inventories, circa 1942-1950; 5.1:
    - Hermann Göring Art Collection at Unterstein, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Inventory and Transportation of Looted Art from Berchtesgaden, Altausee and Other Repositories, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Inventories at Weisbaden and Munich Central Collecting Points, circa 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Inventory of Art Lost in Flak Tires Fires, Berlin, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reports, 1944-1949; 5.2:
    These are official reports related to the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives (MFAA) Section and its responsibilities and findings. There are some official MFAA status reports concerning issues at the Weisbaden Central Collecting Point, but the bulk of the reports are about the MFAA investigation of looted artwork and repatriation efforts after the war.
    - Official Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Status Reports, circa 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Art Looting Investigation Unit Final Report, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - International Protection of Works of Art and Historic Monuments, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Report on 202 Paintings Belonging to the Berlin Museums in the United States of America, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Constable Report on Military Government and Visual Arts, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Printed Materials, 1944-1947; 5.3:
    These records consist of a photocopy of a map of the Altaussee salt mines; a manual of maps showing the locations of various cultural monuments in Germany; a military government information bulletin; and a book of military government regulations applying to the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives section.
    - Civil Affairs Handbook: Germany, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Oversized manual of maps housed in OV 6.
    - Map of Altaussee Salt Mines, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Oversized map housed in Box 5, Folder 2.
    - Military Government Weekly Information Bulletin, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Military Government Regulations: Title 18: Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Oversized Map of Altaussee Salt Mines from Box 3, Folder 31, circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Oversized Civil Affairs Handbook: Germany from Box 3, Folder 30, 1944 (Box OV 6)
- Photographs, 1938-1970; Series 6; 1.2 Linear feet Box 3-5
  Found here are photographs documenting Howe's work in the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section and personal photographs. Many of the photographs have hand-written or typed annotations on the verso.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  Subseries 6.1: Monuments, Fine Arts, and Archives Section Photographs, 1940-1949
  Subseries 6.2: Personal Photographs, 1938-1970
  - Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section Photographs, 1940-1949; 6.1:
    There are many photographs documenting bomb damage to cultural monuments during World War II, mostly in Germany though there are a few in Austria and France; art recovery at the Altaussee salt mines in Austria, as well as the Berchtesgaden and the Neuschwanstein castle in Germany; transportation of famous artwork such as Michelangelo's The Madonna and Child, also known as the Bruges Madonna, and Hubert and Jan van Eyck's Adoration of the Mystic Lamb, also known as the Ghent Altarpiece; restitution activities at Wiesbaden and Munich Central Collecting Points, mostly storing and packing crates of recovered art; and photographs of artwork.
    Howe and fellow Monuments Man James Rorimer exchanged photographs of bomb damage to cultural monuments for research purposes, since they both wrote books about their MFAA experiences after the war. Consequently, some of the photographs are labelled "James J. Rorimer" on the verso.
    There are many photographs of the Monuments Men, including Thomas Carr Howe, George Stout, Stephen Kovalyak, Bancel LaFarge, Lamont Moore, Patrick J. Kelleher, Edith Standen, and Rose Valland.
    The photographs are grouped together by subject, such as documentation of bomb damage according to the country, looted art repositories, and collecting points for art restitutions. The photographs taken by James Rorimer are also grouped together. Miscellaneous photographs of unidentified locations or sight-seeing can be found toward the end of the subseries.
    - Nazi Art Looting in Process, circa 1944; 2 Photographs (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Bomb Damage and Cultural Monuments in Belgium, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Includes photographs of bomb damage to the interior of La Glieze Church.
    - Cultural Monuments in Paris, France, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Includes photographs of Place Stanislas, St. Joan of Arc Basilica, and the Arc de Triomphe.
    - Bomb Damage and Cultural Monuments in German Cities (Box 3)
      - Aachen, Ahrweiler, Ansbach, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Bad Wildungen, Bonn, Bruhl, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Cologne and Crottorf, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Fritzler, Furstenberg, Hildesheim, Julich, Kassel, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Langenau, Limburg, Marburg, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Maria Laach, Merode, Monschau, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Before and After Photographs of Buildings Damaged in Nuremberg, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Satzvey, Weimar, Wilhelmstal, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Unidentified Locations, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Bomb Damage Photographs Taken by James Rorimer, circa 1945 (Box 3)
      - Innsbruck Church, Austria, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Berchtesgaden, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Darmstadt, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Frankfurt Cathedral, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Munich, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Rothenburg Town Hall, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Ulm Cathedral, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "German Vandalism" at Chateaus in France, Photographs Taken by James Rorimer, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Photographs of the interior and exterior of 2 chateaus left in disorder after being occupied by Nazi soldiers, labeled "German Vandalism" on the verso.
    - Altaussee, Austria, 1945 (Box 3)
      - Altaussee Environs, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 54)
        Photographs of the mountains, valleys, and lakes in the area.
      - Altaussee Village, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Salt Mine Buildings, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - George Stout at the Entrance to the Salt Mine, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Thomas Carr Howe, George Stout, and Karl Sieber Inside the Mines, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Mine Workers and Soldiers with Recovered Paintings, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - Mine Workers and Art Restorer Karl Sieber, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Ghent Altarpiece Inspected by Daniel Kern and Karl Sieber, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Packing and Tranporting the Bruges Madonna, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 62)
        Includes photographs of Monuments Men Thomas Carr Howe, George Stout, and Stephen Kovalyak.
      - Soldiers Loading Art onto Trucks, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - Photographs of Artwork, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Berchtesgaden, Germany (Box 3)
      - Thomas Carr Howe, Lamont Moore, and Stephen Kovalyak at the Göring Collection Repository, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - Soldiers Loading Statues onto Truck, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 66)
        Includes a photograph of Stephen Kovalyak.
      - Photographs of Paintings from Göring Collection, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Neuschwanstein Castle, Germany (Box 4)
      - Views of the Castle from Up Close and Far Away, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Storage Room and Throne Room, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Soldiers Loading Crates of Art During Autumn and Winter Art Recovery, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Loading Art from Neuschwanstein onto Trains at Fussen, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Trucks Transporting Art from Hohenfurth to Munich, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Monuments Men Group Photograph, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Photograph include Walker Hancock, Lamont Moore, George Stout, and 2 others.
    - John Walker and Bancel LaFarge at Unterstein, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Photographer in Studio with Art from the Göring Collection at Unterstein, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Eagle's Nest or Kehlsteinhaus, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of John Walker, Thomas Carr Howe, Bancel LaFarge, and Harry Anderson.
    - Art Recovery at Graslaben Salt Mine, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Art Conservator at Unidentified Location, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Munich Collecting Point (Box 4)
      - Plane Loaded with Shipment of Art to Holland, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Ghent Altarpiece Loaded onto a Truck and Plane, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
        Includes photographs of Thomas Carr Howe, Stephen Kovalyak, Lamont Moore, Robert Posey, and Craig Smyth.
      - Packing and Loading Art Shipment to France, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Storage Rooms and Packing Art, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Thomas Carr Howe, Lamont Moore, and Guard at the Amalienburg, Munich, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Wiesbaden Collecting Point (Box 4)
      - Storage Rooms for Art, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Packing and Loading Art Restitution Shipment to France, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 18)
        Includes photographs of Edith Standen and Rose Valland, as well as Aristide Maillol sculptures.
      - Art Restitution Shipment to Belgium, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 19)
        Includes photographs of Edith Standen and Raymond Lemaire.
      - MFAA Officials Inspecting Art, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 20)
        Includes photographs of Edith Standen, Rose Valland and one photograph of Patrick "Joe" Kelleher.
      - Hungarian Crown Jewels, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 21)
        Includes photograph of Edith Standen and Patrick "Joe" Kelleher.
      - Edith Standen Conducting Tour of Guards, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Exhibitions of Recovered Art, 1946-1949 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Photographs of the Bust of Nefertiti, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Photographs of Artwork and Cultural Artifacts, circa 1946 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Photographs of Art and Cultural Artifacts, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Frankfurt and Environs, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Wies Church, Germany, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Linderhof Palace, Germany, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Schloss Wilhelmshohe and Schloss Wilhelmsthal, Germany, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      4 small snapshots, includes Thomas Carr Howe, Patrick "Joe" Kelleher, and Edith Standen.
    - Miscellaneous Locations, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Photographs of Han van Meegeren Paintings, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Photograph of Hermann Göring and Relative, circa 1945 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Personal Photographs, 1938-1970; 6.2:
    This series contains portraits of Howe as well as events and parties he attended. Howe appears in the majority of the photographs along with his wife Francesca. Many photographs have annotations on the verso but frequently do not identify the event.
    - Thomas Carr Howe Portraits, circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      Oversized material housed in Box 5, Folder 3.
    - 10th Anniversary of the United Nations, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Events and Parties, 1938-1958 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      Oversized material housed in box 5, folder 4.
    - Events and Parties, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Events and Parties, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Inaugural Exhibition, "Art Treasures in California," 1969 November 30-1970 January 1, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous Undated Events, circa 1946-1970 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Oversized Portraits from Box 4, Folder 34, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Photograph from Box 4, Folder 36, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook, 1936-1948; Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet Box 4
  This scrapbook is filled with news clippings on celebrities, such as Joe Di Maggio, socialites, and various events. The bulk of the clippings appear to be about entertainment and contain jokes, advice columns, and movie advertisements. Only a few articles, largely anecdotal, reference World War II. There is one news clipping with a photo of Howe's wife Francesca.
  The scrapbook was dismantled and separated into three folders for preservation purposes.
  - Dismantled Scrapbook, 1936-1948; 3 Folders (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
- Printed Materials, 1934-1980; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Box 4
  Printed materials includes news clippings and miscellaneous records such as postcards, benefit and fundraising papers, memorial tributes, etc. The news clippings cover topics such as Monuments Men activities and discoveries, art exhibitions, reviews for Salt Mines and Castles, and information about various art dealers and collectors. This series also contains essays, postcards, memorial tributes for colleagues, fundraising information packets, and a file of information on the provenance of a painting.
  The news clippings are grouped together chronologically, followed by miscellaneous printed materials.
  - News Clippings, 1934-1941 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - News Clippings, 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - News Clippings, 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - News Clippings, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - News Clippings, 1967-1978 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1934-1978 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Booklets, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Postcards, circa 1949 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Art Benefit and Fundraiser Announcements and Programs, circa 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Memorial Tributes, circa 1973 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Information about Portrait of a Man by Sir Joshua Reynolds, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 54)